<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An answer to the letter to a dissenter, detecting the many unjust insinuations which highly reflect on His Majesty, as likewise the many false charges on the dissenters. Published with allowance.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1687</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 36 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 7 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A69475</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3416A</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R14774</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99825040</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99825040</idno>
            <idno type="VID">29407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A69475)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 29407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 629:7; 1754:12)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An answer to the letter to a dissenter, detecting the many unjust insinuations which highly reflect on His Majesty, as likewise the many false charges on the dissenters. Published with allowance.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>12 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed by Henry Hills, printer to the King's most Excellent Majesty, for His houshold and chappel; and are sold at his Printing-house on the Ditch-side in Black-Fryers,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1687.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A reply to: George Saville, 1st Marquis of Halifax.  A letter to a dissenter.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the University of Illinois (Urbana-Champaign Campus). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>James --  II, --  King of England, 1633-1701 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Halifax, George Savile, --  Marquis of, 1633-1695. --  Letter to a dissenter.</term>
               <term>Dissenters, Religious --  England --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  James II, 1685-1688 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-08</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:29407:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:29407:1"/>
            <p>AN ANSWER TO THE <hi>Letter to a Diſſenter,</hi> Detecting the many UNJUST INSINUATIONS Which highly Reflect on His Majeſty, As likewiſe the many falſe Charges on the DISSENTERS.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Publiſhed with Allowance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Henry Hills,</hi> Printer to the King's Moſt Excellent Majeſty, for His Houſhold and Chappel; And are ſold at his Printing houſe on the Ditch-ſide in <hi>Black-Fryers.</hi> 1687.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:29407:2"/>
            <pb n="3" facs="tcp:29407:2"/>
            <head>AN ANSWER TO THE <hi>LETTER</hi> to a <hi>DISSENTER,</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>THE Letter to a Diſſenter upon occaſion of his Majeſty's late Graci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Declaration of Indulgence, I have in obedience to your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand carefully perus'd, and muſt aſſure you, that the returning an Anſwer, tho' very eaſie, is yet unpleaſant: For, as its Author has not offer'd any thing that is cloſe and nervous, yet he has larded his Diſcourſe with ſo many unjuſt Inſinuations of what highly re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>flects on his Majeſty, and with ſo many falſe Charges on the Diſſenter, that a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hearſal of 'em, which is neceſſary for the Anſwerer to give, cannot well be, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs with ſuch ſmart Repartees as may look over-ſevere, at leaſt to ſome of the Author's Admirers.</p>
            <p>There is nothing more hateful unto me, than the dropping one word in any Concertation, that may look hard, and finding it impoſſible to give a full Anſwer to this Letter, without expreſſing thoſe juſt Reſentments the whole Contexture of his Harangue have made neceſſary, I ſhould have been very glad to have been Diſpens'd with. But the Conſideration of the Service I may do his Majeſty and the whole Kingdom, by detecting the Vanity and Folly of the Author in connexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on with your Injunctions, hath emboldned me to Reſolve on as calm a Diſcuſſion of this Letter, as the Subject matter of it will admit.</p>
            <p>The whole of this Letter I find may be reduc'd to theſe Heads: <hi>Falſe Charges againſt the Diſſenter, Vile Reflections on his Majeſty,</hi> and An Intimation of the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> Repentance, with ſome little Artifices made uſe of to inveagle the Diſſenter to act contrary to his avow'd Principles, and real Intereſt.</p>
            <p>This I take to be a full Account of the Pamphlet, to all which I will give my Replies diſtinctly.</p>
            <p>To begin with his Charge againſt the Diſſenter, as what is of leaſt moment, and at which the Pamphleteer would only glance, and introduce it by way of Suppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſition, that, if poſſible, whenever occaſion ſhould make it neceſſary, he might, by ſaying he did not poſitively affirm it, fetch himſelf off from the reproach of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:29407:3"/> a Falſe Accuſer; but this way of reproaching the Innocent is ſo common, that by wiſe Men the very Inſinuation, where the Charge cannot be made good, is look'd on as very Unjuſt and Abuſive. However, after this manner the <hi>Excluſion</hi> and <hi>Late Rebellion</hi> is laid at <hi>the Diſſenter's Door,</hi> and <hi>their Miniſters ſuppos'd to have Mony ſprinkled amongſt them, to engage the People firſt one way, and now another, and therefore their Reaſonings are not to be regarded, eſpecially if they preach up Anger and Vengeance againſt the Church of</hi> England; <hi>That their Addreſſes don't flow from a Senſe of his Majeſty's Kindneſs,</hi> but <hi>from the Perſuaſions</hi> or <hi>Threatnings us'd to obtain 'em; that tho' the Diſſenters are againſt SET-FORMS of Prayer, yet are now content the Prieſts ſhould indite for them;</hi> and <hi>inſtead of ſilently receiving the benefit of Indulgence, they ſet up for Advocates to ſupport it, and become voluntary Aggreſſors, and look like Counſel Retain'd by the Prerogative againſt their old Friend MAGNA CHARTA.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This is one part of the Gentleman's Letter, and theſe are the chief Reaſons he preſſes the Diſſenters with, to engage them againſt an accepting the Liberty his Majeſty has moſt Graciouſly given them. It's this that is at bottom; for, (ſaith he) <hi>It might be wiſh'd that they would have ſuppreſſed their Impatience, and have been content for the ſake of Religion, to enjoy it within themſelves without the Liberty of a Public Exerciſe, till a Parliament had allow'd it.</hi> But I'll appeal to any conſidering Man of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Communion, whether the Method this Gentleman has taken to wheedle the Diſſenter, be either <hi>Chriſtian</hi> or <hi>Prudent:</hi> For, what of Chriſtianity is there in charging the Innocent, as being guilty of the moſt odious Crimes; or what of Prudence in railing on thoſe whom they would enſnare into a Compliance with them?</p>
            <p>In the firſt place the <hi>Excluſion</hi> is charg'd on the Diſſenters, and (as another Pamphleteer has it) it's the <hi>Nonconformiſts that by their medling in the Matter of the Excluſion drew a new Storm upon themſelves.</hi> And why muſt the Matter of the Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion be charg'd on the Diſſenters? Was not that thing manag'd in the Houſe of Commons by the Sons of the Church of <hi>England?</hi> Were not the chief Speakers in that Houſe Church of <hi>England</hi>-men, and thoſe who made up that Houſe, ten to one, of her Communion? It has been, I confeſs, a common Practice for the Church of <hi>England,</hi> to do a bad thing, and throw the Odium on't on the Diſſenter; but is this fair or juſt? If going ordinarily to the Common-Prayer, and taking the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament according to the Uſage of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> be a Teſt by which we may know one of her Communion, the Matter of the Excluſion muſt lie at her Door; And if thus much be not enough to Characterize a Churchman, what is? She'll not (I hope) inſiſt on the Doctrin of <hi>Non-reſiſtance,</hi> as what is peculiar to Men of her Religion, leſt thereby the new Maſters of the Ceremonies, that are for a Repeal of the Teſt-Laws, be included within her Pale.</p>
            <p>The ſame may be ſaid of the <hi>Rebellion,</hi> but the Replier to the <hi>Oxford Clergies Reaſons againſt Addreſſing</hi> having fully clear'd up this Matter, I will wave it, being aſſur'd that the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath no reaſon to Glory, as if none of her Sons nor Clergy had any hand in it.</p>
            <p>Ay, but the <hi>Diſſenting Miniſters have Moneys given 'em to carry on the Deſign.</hi> But where is the Man who has receiv'd one Farthing from the <hi>Roman-Catholic</hi> for car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rying on any Popiſh Intrigue? This looks like an old Story, which ſome Years ago was ſpread by a Dignifi'd Clergy-man within the Line of Communication, who was ſo bold as to faſten it on a worthy Gentleman now dead, but who at that time
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:29407:3"/> gave Challenge, which was not during his Life, nor to this hour, taken up. And what is it that tempts this ſort of Men to talk after the old rate? Have they any new Inſtances that makes 'em ſo brisk in their Accuſations? Let them make it out againſt one Nonconforming Miniſter, or forbear this Invidious way of caſting Reproach on the Guiltleſs.</p>
            <p>However, for once let us ſuppoſe that ſome Diſſenting Miniſters have receiv'd Mony from thoſe in Authority for ſome Service they did the Government, What is this to the promoting a Popiſh Deſign? Multitudes of the Church of <hi>England</hi> have been raiſed to great Preferments for the Services they were ſuppoſed to have done the Government, but was it in good earneſt becauſe they promoted Popery? This Letter inſinuates, as if the <hi>Papiſts alſo promoted the late Perſecution againſt Diſſenters,</hi> and yet we remember well, who Preach'd up Perſecution be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Lord Major of this City, and who alſo was made a Dean: But was it becauſe he deſigned Popery? Moreover it's well known, that a certain Biſhop in the World, if one under a ſuſpenſion ſtill bears that Name, who procur'd at leaſt 200 <hi>l.</hi> to encourage a Church of <hi>England Doctor</hi> to perſecute the Non-confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts, and was this for the ſake of Popery? In a word, we give the Challenge to any Man to prove that the Papiſt did at any time give one Farthing to a Diſſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Miniſter; or that the Diſſenters did Receive from the Government the for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieth part that Church of <hi>England</hi> Miniſters have received.</p>
            <p>If any Church of <hi>England</hi> Men have been ſenſible of the Miſeries they have by their ſevere Laws expos'd the Diſſenters unto, and in compaſſion have given ſome Relief, the Diſſenters no doubt will thankfully acknowledge it, but then they muſt add, that unleſs the Church of <hi>England</hi> Men muſt be eſteemed Papiſts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe of the Alliance there is between their Principles, this is not a receiving Mony from Papiſts: But let the Truth be brought to Light, and let the Church of <hi>England</hi> Charity to Diſſenting Miniſters be diſcovered, and 'twill appear that it's not to be compared with what the Church of <hi>England</hi> hath taken from 'em. Moreover it's well known, that when ſome Gentlemen on their Dying Reds to expreſs their Affection to Diſſenting Miniſters have given 'em Legacies, they have been depriv'd of 'em. And where is the Diſſenting Miniſter, <hi>who Preaches up Anger and Vengeance againſt the Church of</hi> England? Name the Man, that we may know who he is, and what repute he has amongſt the party; and 'twould be alſo an Act of Juſtice in him to direct us to the People who receiv'd their Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſes from a Prieſt, and to the Prieſt that made 'em.</p>
            <p>If the Gentleman cannot clear up theſe Points, as I preſume he cannot, how ſpecious ſoever his pretences may be, his untruth won't much advantage the Church of <hi>England,</hi> nor will that Church have much cauſe to Glory in ſuch an Advocate, who doth not only charge her for Perſecuting the Diſſenter, but makes no other Plea, but what leans on the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>eebleſt Foundation, even on Injuſtice and Falſe Accuſations. And if this be her beſt Refuge, her Quarrel with the King (it's hop'd) cannot hold long, for theſe generally are the laſt.</p>
            <p>And what is it that provokes the good Man to perſuade us, that the <hi>Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters Thanks are Extorted?</hi> Doth he think that the being deliver'd from a violent Perſecution is ſo inconſiderable a kindneſs, that the Diſſenters can't be ſenſible of it? Are grievous Impriſonments, the ſpoiling 'em of their Eſtates, the ruin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of their Families, ſuch ſmall matters, that the Deliverance cannot Merit the Name of a favor? Or, are the Diſſenters ſo uſed to ſuch Calamities and made
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:29407:4"/> ſo Brawny, that they are not capable of perceiving ſo much? Is it impoſſible for them to diſtinguiſh Eaſe from Miſery? If ſo, whoſe fault is that? Is it not the Perſecutors that have ſo ill intreated them? It's true the Church of <hi>England</hi> did by her Rigour, ſo over-aw them, that they durſt not Petition the King for eaſe; and after his Majeſty moſt Graciouſly gave it them, the Dread and Confuſion they remained under was ſo very great, that the Diſſenters could not eaſily recover themſelves, and make that haſt they ſhould, to render the King their humbleſt thanks. But this is not for the Honor of the Church, firſt to frighten the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and make him move ſlowly, and then reproach him for not making more haſte. And this is not all, for the Diſſenters do no ſooner Addreſs, but they become <hi>Voluntary Aggreſſors,</hi> and look like Counſel retain'd by the Prerogative againſt <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> This is a run from one Extream to another, they are firſt charg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for not rendring thanks <hi>willingly,</hi> and yet then are made <hi>Voluntary</hi> Aggreſſors for rendring ſuch unwilling thanks, who look like Counſel retain'd againſt <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> Are not the Diſſenters then in a moſt deplorable condition? If they do not Addreſs, they are a People that can never be oblig'd by benefits, nor fit to be Tolerated, as one Church Doctor aſſures them; if they do Addreſs, they are for Prerogative againſt <hi>Magna Charta.</hi> And why againſt <hi>Magna Charta?</hi> Is it againſt the Great Charter of <hi>England,</hi> that a good Subject enjoy his Civil Rights, and Properties? The Diſſenters, at leaſt the greateſt part of 'em, take the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, and thereby ſhew themſelves to be good Subjects, and why then muſt they be depriv'd of their Civil Rights, for the ſake of a Religion that hurts not the Government? Some ſay, that by the Fundamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tal Conſtitution of our Government all Laws againſt the Law of God are <hi>ipſo facto</hi> void and null, and may not the King prevent the Execution of ſuch vacated Laws? Others tell us, that to be of this, or that, or the other Religion, is not a Crime at Common Law, it is but <hi>Malum Prohibitum,</hi> and yet Religious Meet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings have been made Routs and Riots, (even the ſuppoſed Intention to ſerve God, hath been thus interpreted) which are <hi>mala in ſe.</hi> And why may not the King prevent theſe abuſes of the Law? The Diſſenter is alſo told, that 'tis a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to diſſeiſe the Subject of his Free-hold or Liberty, but by Lawful Judgment of his Peers, and yet by the <hi>Conventicle Act,</hi> and the <hi>Oxford Act,</hi> the Diſſenters have been diſſeiſed of both without any ſuch Judgment of their Peers, and may not the King hinder this? There have been alſo great Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers who aver, that the 23d. of <hi>Elizabeth</hi> affects not a Proteſtant Diſſenter, and yet many have been ruin'd by this Act, and may not the King put a ſtop to this Injuſtice and Violence on the Subject? It's alſo told them, that 'tis againſt <hi>Magna Charta</hi> to Amerce a Free-man any other ways than after the manner of the fault, ſaying to him his Contenement and Free-hold, and yet Convictions have been, <hi>unknown</hi> to the accus'd party, Recorded, and Warrants have been granted out for 8, 10, 12, or 14 Conventicles at once to the Diſſeiſing the Free-man of all he has. It's true, a great Lawyer declar'd, that no Conviction could be Legally Recorded untill the party accuſed was ſummoned to ſhew cauſe; but another yet living was of another Opinion, and gave life to Clandeſtine Convictions, as a Juſtice of Peace and a great Lawyer did grant out Warrants on Prophetic Oaths, that a Meeting would be the next Day or Week following; But the King has deliver'd them from all theſe Miſeries, and yet may they not give thanks, unleſs they ſet themſelves againſt <hi>Magna Charta?</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:29407:4"/>
            <p>Furthermore it muſt not be forgotten, how much the Church of <hi>England</hi> have exalted the Prerogative when they were in hopes of having it employ'd againſt the Diſſenter, and nothing more certain than that <hi>Qui ſentit commodum, &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>commodum ſentire debet,</hi> and therefore how much ſoever the King Exerciſes his Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, in this reſpect the Church-men muſt be ſilent, and that in matters Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſiaſtical the King can diſpenſe, no Man of Learning that I could ever hear of, but doth acknowledge it, and others affirm, that the King can in matters Civil diſpenſe with whatever is but <hi>malum Prohibitum.</hi> But for theſe things conſult <hi>Nye's Diſcourſe,</hi> and the <hi>Replier to the</hi> Oxford <hi>Reaſons againſt Addreſſing.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In a word, if the King had been of the Church of <hi>England's</hi> Religion, not only the <hi>Diſpenſing</hi> Power, but the <hi>Legiſlative</hi> would have been (as heretofore it has been affirm'd to be) lodg'd in the King's Breaſt; but if the King be of another Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, he muſt be depriv'd of all his Prerogatives: But whatever the preſent ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>timents of the Church of <hi>England</hi> are, it's very manifeſt, that according to the frame of our Government, as deſcrib'd by the Church of <hi>England Men</hi> heretofore, the King could not only diſpenſe with Laws, but the Prerogative is ſo very much above all Laws, that even thoſe Commiſſions granted by Prerogative againſt Statute-Law muſt be regarded more than that Law. It is not therefore the Prerogative that our Church-men are angry with, but the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of it to the Relief of others. Tis the Diſſenters Liberty that vexes them.</p>
            <p>For though it be known, that the Diſſenters lie under manifeſt Convi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions of Conſcience, that it's their Duty to worſhip God in their Way, that their Privacy was but the Effect of a Violence laid upon them, which is no ſooner remov'd, but they return to their Duty; yet for the ſake of Religion, contrary to their Conſciences, they muſt lay aſide the Public Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip of God, and all this to gratifie their Perſecuting Friends of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and muſt wait till a Parliament, that is againſt Liberty of Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, give 'em Liberty. For the great thing the Diſſenters deſire, is a Parliament that will concurr with the King in Eſtabliſhing Liberty by a Law, and for deſiring <hi>ſuch</hi> a Parliament they are expos'd by our Gentleman to the ſevereſt Cenſures.</p>
            <p>But let us ſuppoſe that to gratifie their Perſecutors, the Diſſenters would venture on one ſtretch of Conſcience; and tho when they could not Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip Publickly without Trouble, yet were reſolv'd to hold on in that Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and will now, whil'ſt they may be at eaſe, leave off all Public Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, I ſay, for once let us make the Suppoſition: But then would not this be ſufficient to juſtifie all the Clamors, they have been loaded with above Twenty Years together, of being the moſt giddy and obſtinate People alive, who know not how to live, but in contradiction to the Government; and would not this provoke the King to conclude, that it's not Religion but Faction and Sedition they are for? And would not our Clergy have endea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voured to fix ſuch Thoughts of the Diſſenters on his Majeſties Mind? And might they not have continued their Privacy till Dooms-day for any Relief a Parliament would give 'em? How then can any Man of Conſcience, or of mere Humanity, be angry with this perſecuted People, becauſe they thankfully accept of Liberty, and are deſirous that it may be Eſtabliſhed by Law? But this is not the worſt part of the Pamphlet, there remaineth what cannot but turn the Stomach of any Loyal Perſon againſt it; for Reflexi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:29407:5"/> of a more odious Nature cannot be caſt on any Man of Honor, than this Pamphleteer has caſt on the King.</p>
            <p>In the Firſt place, he inſinuates that the <hi>King gives not the Diſſenter this Liberty, of Inclination, but of Neceſſity. Theſe New Friends,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>by whom he muſt mean his Majeſty, and thoſe of his Religion, did not make you their</hi> Choice, <hi>but their Refuge, they have ever made their firſt Courtſhips to the Church of</hi> England, <hi>and when they were rejected there, they made their Application to you in the Second place; that the King being a Papiſt, is not to be believed; for the Papiſts are no more able to make good their Vows, than</hi> Men <hi>married before and their Wife alive, can confirm their Contract with another. Beſides, he</hi> further ſuggeſts, as <hi>if his Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty would imitate a Neighbouring Prince, in deſtroying all Proteſtants; for</hi> he ſaith, If <hi>in the Heighth of this great Dearneſs, by comparing things, it ſhould happen, that at this Inſtant there is much a ſurer Friendſhip with thoſe who are ſo far from al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Liberty, that they allow no Living to a Proteſtant under them:</hi> Let <hi>the Scene lie in what part of the world it will, the Argument will come home, and ſure it will afford ſufficient ground to ſuſpect.</hi> And in another Page, the <hi>Prerogative is brought in retaining Counſel againſt</hi> Magna Charta, and <hi>in anſwer to an Objection, in which 'tis ſaid, that the Church of</hi> England <hi>is never humble, but when ſhe is out of Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; The Reply is, That this is not ſo in FACT;</hi> For <hi>whatever may be told the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter at this very Hour, and in the Heat and Glare of their Sun-ſhine, the Church of</hi> England <hi>can in a moment bring Clouds again, and turn the Royal Thunder upon their Heads, blow 'em off the Stage with a breath, if ſhe ſhould give but a ſmile or a kind word, the least glimps of her Compliance, would throw them back into the State of Suffering, and draw upon 'em all the Arrears of Severity, which have accrued during the Time of this Kindneſs to them.</hi> But this is not all, for it is further inſinuated, as <hi>if the next Parliament ſhall be choſen by the King, and not by the People,</hi> that <hi>no Liberty of Debate ſhall be left the Members of either Houſe, but the Roman Conſiſtory ſhall be made Lords of the Articles.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All this, and much more is to be found in the Pamphlet, and what can be the meaning of all this, But that the Bigotted part of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> if ever they were Loyal, are faln from their Loyalty, and have out-done the moſt Seditious Scriblers? For what can be ſaid worſe of any Prince? What was ever ſaid worſe of <hi>Charles the Second,</hi> by any Factious Party? Or what can be ſaid worſe of any Man living? The Laſhes given our King are moſt ſevere, and look like an Interpretation of their Doctrin of Non-reſiſtance. And if a Fear that others ſhall enjoy but a like Eaſe with them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, ſtir up all this Choler againſt their Sovereign, may we not fairly conclude, that if they had been in that Suffering Condition the Diſſenters have been for Six and Twenty Years together, they would have ſtirred up many a Rebellion? And what ſhall we think of thoſe, who ſo very much applaud all this, as too many of the Church of <hi>England</hi> Communion have done? But do theſe Gentlemen think that this is the way to take with Diſſenters? Will they, who by their Sufferings for many Years together could never be provok'd, will they (I ſay), now <hi>their Sorrows are removed,</hi> imitate ſuch Church-men, and flie in his Majeſties Face for the Grace he affords 'em? If you think they are ſo like your ſelves, Time will demonſtrate your Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtake. For to be under a Prince of a Different Religion from themſelves is no new thing to them, they have known how to ſuffer under ſuch, and how
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:29407:5"/> to enjoy Peace and Quiet when it's their Princes Pleaſure to give it 'em, and they cannot but pity you, to ſee how you wince and kick, aſſoon as you find your Prince doth in good earneſt diſlike your Religion and Conduct.</p>
            <p>And how is it that this Gentleman dares to contradict his Sovereign? The <hi>King declares that it has been a long time his Principle,</hi> that <hi>Conſcience ought not to be conſtrain'd, nor Men puniſhed for m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>er Religion,</hi> and <hi>that it has been againſt his Royal Inclination to perſecute any for their Conſciences,</hi> and <hi>alſo his Reſolve that if ever it came into his Power, he would put a ſtop unto it, as he now has done,</hi> and whoſe Word is to be regarded? That of a Prince, who knows beſt his own Heart, and whoſe Word, till the Time that he ſhewed Mercy to the Diſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter, has been entirely depended on by the Church of <hi>England,</hi> or this Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mans, whom we have found to inſinuate ſeveral Falſities in this very Pamphlet?</p>
            <p>But he ſaith that in the <hi>firſt place they courted the Church of</hi> England. And for what? Was it not to preſs them to be willing, to take off all Penal Laws and Teſts, in purſuance of his Majeſties moſt Chriſtian Principle? And if your Church of <hi>England</hi> has been ſo obſtinate in oppoſing not only ſo great a Prince, but ſo Chriſtian a Principle, muſt the Diſſenter take pett, becauſe they were not firſt Courted? No Sir, the Church of <hi>Englands</hi> rejecting the Applications made to her ſufficiently diſcovers her Reſolution to abide by her old Doctrin of Perſecution, and therefore the Diſſenters have the greateſt Reaſon in the World to beware leſt they loſe this Opportunity, and fall under the laſh of your Penal Laws once more. They can't forget how oft you have ſaid, that the Papiſts are much better than the Presbyterians, and that you would rather turn Papiſt than Presbyterian, and they are ſtill afraid, that your not complying with the King, is, becauſe you long for another op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity to perſecute afreſh.</p>
            <p>'Tis true we know that amongſt the Gentry of your Communion there are many Reſolv'd to do their utmoſt for the Eaſe of the Diſſenters, and they have, as there was occaſion, expreſs'd their Diſlike of violent Methods to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince rational Men; but amongſt the Clergy, there is only a ſprinkling here and there, and at this very Time many can't forbear their Railing againſt Diſſenters, but of this more by and by.</p>
            <p>You in the next place tell us, that <hi>Papiſts are no more able to make good their Vows, than Men married before, and their Wife alive, can confirm their Contract with another.</hi> And is this conſiſtent with your Addreſſes of Thanks for his Maje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties Declaration by which he promiſed to protect the Church of <hi>England?</hi> What, are there no Men of Honor amongſt the Engliſh Papiſts? What, no Regard to be had to the Word of a King if a Papiſt? Is not this a caſting dirt in his Majeſties Face? Were it needful, I could give you ſeveral In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Men of Honor and Truth to their Word amongſt Papiſts, and I know of none that ever doubted it, when it was for their Intereſt as it is in this Caſe.</p>
            <p>But who can without horror conſider that wretched Inſinuation by which our Prince is linked with another who will not ſuffer a Proteſtant to live within his Government? Methinks this Liberty which ſo very much diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſes the Gentleman, ſhould convince him of his Madneſs. Our Prince is not only of a contrary Principle, but has had the Advantage of ſeeing the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:29407:6"/> miſchievous Effects of Perſecution, not only at home, but abroad, and therefore takes quite contrary meaſures, and yet he is to be ſuſpected. Verily if a Diſſenter had ſaid half ſo much of <hi>Charles</hi> the Second, every Pulpit would have rung on't, and have condemned him for a Traitor, a Rebel, and what not, and that without the Help of <hi>Innuendo's.</hi> They would have ſaid, What can more evidently diſcover the Deſigns and Purpoſes of their Hearts, when they repreſent their Sovereign under ſo black a Character? But theſe very Men think they have a Priviledge and may innocently Revile the Lords Anointed, and therefore they go on to tell the World, that the <hi>Prerogative is retaining Counſel againſt</hi> Magna Charta, as if the King intended nothing leſs than the Raviſhing his People of their Civil Rights and Priviledges, even becauſe he endeavours ſtrenuouſly their Reſtoration and Eſtabliſhment.</p>
            <p>The King would have all things reduced to the ancient Conſtitution of our Government, therefore would have none of his good Subjects depriv'd of their Civil Rights for the ſake of their Religion, and would by all means have Liberty and Property to be look'd on, as too Sacred to be touch'd for an harmleſs Opinion, and yet becauſe this diſpleaſes our perſecuting Clergy it muſt be interpreted a ſetting up Prerogative againſt <hi>Magna Charta.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that the Diſſenter may underſtand the Reaſon of all this Boldneſs with their King, the Gentleman aſſures us they have him at their Command. He is perfectly a Dependant on them, and that becauſe they frown, the King runs unto the Diſſenter for Refuge, but if they would but ſmile, or ſpeak a kind Word, 'twould be enough to engage Him to forget all his Promiſes and turn the Royal Thunder againſt the Diſſenter. Thus he firſt repreſents the King's Religion to be ſuch as raſes all Principles of Honor and Truth out of his Royal Heart, and then tells us, that the King's Caſe is ſo deſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and deplorable, that tho he is now gone to the Diſſenter for Shelter, yet if the Church of <hi>England,</hi> will give him one ſmile, he'l break all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes he made them, and notwithſtanding the King has promiſed his Pardon for all that is paſt, their ſmile, or a kind word from them would draw upon the Diſſenters all the Arrears of Severity. But who can read this with leſs Horror, than I am in at the writing it? If this be Church of <hi>England</hi> Loy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>alty, I muſt make uſe of this Litany, <hi>From Church of</hi> England <hi>Loyalty, good Lord deliver me.</hi> For after what a diſmal rate do they paint out our Prince? and if our Prince had been ſuch an One, in what a calamitous Condition would the Engliſh be? I dread the Rehearſal of it, and therefore I will on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly apply my ſelf unto the Engliſh Gentry, who moſt undoubtedly will diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover their Abhorrence of all ſuch ſcurrilous Pamplets, and muſt beſeech them to conſider what a plunge this Gentleman would hurry both them and the Diſſenters into, could he but obtain his aime; eſpecially conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing how he would perſwade us to believe that the King deſigns to ſend down his <hi>Congè d' Eſlire to every County, City, and Corporation in the Kingdom, for the Choice of Parliament-men, and take away the Liberty of Debate from the Members of both Houſes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Truth of it is, the Gentleman has not ſpared to blacken the King, and thereby has acted the part of a brisk Clergy-man very notably; for who could believe what this Man ſaith, and not immediately endeavor a preſent Freedom from the Oppreſſion that he muſt have in proſpect? But the Diſſenters knowing
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:29407:6"/> how much he loads them, and their Miniſters with his falſe charges, and feel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Grace and Clemency of the King in reſcuing 'em out of the Hand of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> are abundantly ſatisfied both of the Impudence and Ill De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſign of the Pamphleteer.</p>
            <p>And as he doth thus treat the Diſſenter and his Moſt Sacred Majeſty, ſo, that he might leave no Artifice unattempted, he would fain lick over the Sores of his beloved Perſecutors, and ſaith, <hi>If you had now to do with thoſe Rigid Prelates, who made it matter of Conſcience to give you the leaſt Indulgence, but kept you at an uncharitable Diſtance, and even to your more Reaſonable ſcruples continue stiff and inexorable, the Argument might be fairer on your ſide, but ſince the Common danger hath ſo laid open that miſtake, that all the former haughtineſs towards you is for ever extinguiſhed, and that it hath turned the Spirit of Perſecution into a Spirit of Peace, Charity and Condeſcention.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In anſwer hereunto, I am glad to find any Man, who ſeems Zealous for the Engliſh Clergy, as this Gentleman doth, to be ſo ſenſible, that <hi>the Clergy have been rigid, that they have made it a matter of Conſcience to give the leaſt Indulgence, and that they have been Proud and Haughty.</hi> But I am afraid that few of the Perſecuting Clergy are ſo ſenſible of their Error as this Man would have us believe, for it's manifeſt that there are many of 'em, who continue their old Pulpit Railings, and whilſt their hands are tyed, their Tongues and Pens are at work. With what ſcorn and contempt do they expreſs themſelves, when they ſpeak of a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter, and how do they dayly threaten, that they hope for a time to be Reveng'd on them for accepting of Deliverance from their Violence? And at this time they do their utmoſt to prevent their Aſſembling themſelves together for public Worſhip, and as the Perſecution began in a turning the Diſſenter out of the Halls, ſo where the Clergy can prevail, there none are permitted the Conveni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences of theſe places; and where they have Tabernacles to diſpoſe of, they'l let 'em Rot or commit them to the Flames, rather than that the Diſſenters ſhall have the Advantage of Building Convenient Meeting-houſes with them; yea, one of the moſt renowned of their Dignified Clergy would rather the Pariſh ſhould bear the loſs of an Hundred pounds, than part with a Tabernacle to any Man, that would not give bond, not to employ any part of it towards the Building a Meeting-houſe for Diſſenters. And is it not Natural to conclude, that as they at this very time do their utmoſt to diſcourage the Diſſenter, they would ſtill do much more had it been in their Power? Beſides, we have the greateſt reaſon to conclude, that thoſe of the Clergy who are for the giving eaſe to the Diſſenter will take the opportunity, and fall in with the King, and not talk after the rate this Man doth, nor act after the manner theſe others do.</p>
            <p>Really Sir, I am almoſt tir'd, and therefore muſt beg your Pardon, that I only obſerve further to you how apparent it is from what this Gentleman inſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth on, that our Perſecuting Clergy have been the <hi>Papiſts Tool's; Think a little,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>who they were that promoted your Former Perſecutions, and then conſider, how it will look, to be Angry with the</hi> Inſtruments, <hi>and at the ſame time to make a League with the</hi> Authors <hi>of your ſufferings?</hi> So that the Papiſts are ſaid to be the promoters of the Perſecution, and the Church of <hi>England</hi> their Inſtruments, their Tools; and if the Papiſts be driving on ill deſigns, what can they deſire more than that all things ſhould run into confuſion, and let the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land</hi> take heed they be not their Tools in this too. And why muſt not the Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenter
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:29407:7"/> enter into a League with the Papiſts to put a ſtop to all Perſecutions? The Church of <hi>England,</hi> it's like, entred into a League with them in the Perſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuting work, but the Diſſenter muſt not joyn with them in endeavoring the peace and quiet of the Nation. Verily this ſort of Men are greatly to be pityed; and I being heartily ſorrowful for their misfortune, muſt beg leave to tell you, that in the midſt of all this noiſe the True State of the Caſe lies here; the Church of <hi>England</hi> Clergy are for joyning with the Papiſts in a freſh perſecution, but the Papiſts, and the Proteſtant Diſſenters are agreed to do their utmoſt to prevent all Perſecutions for the future in this Land, and this is the thing that vexes our humble and good Natur'd Clergy, and the Attempt of the Author of this Letter is to wheedle the Diſſenters, and perſuade them to give all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tenance they can to the Perſecuting Clergy. But how Wiſely, let the Reader Judge.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>I am Yours.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>POSTSCRIPT.</head>
            <p>If the Gentleman be not ſatisfied with thus much, but is reſolved to continue his Falſe Charges, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> He ſhall have enough in my next to let the World know what manner of Men our Clergy and their Creatures are.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:29407:7"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
